<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<articles>

	<article>
		<title>Our favourite baby names in 2015</title>
		<author>Stephanie Hansen</author>
		<startDate>02/02/2015</startDate>
		<category>Entertainment</category>
		<leadText>Wills and Kate clearly love the name Charlotte. And
			Australians are fans too. The classic name is one of the most popular
			baby names right now. See the full list here.</leadText>
		<fullText>The Duke and Duchess of Cambridge clearly love the name
			Charlotte, yesterday naming their little princess Charlotte Elizabeth
			Diana in a fitting tribute to the ‘People’s Princess’. And Aussies
			are also fans of the classic name. It’s the second most popular baby
			name in Australia right now, according to new data from McCrindle.
			The data was sourced from the Births, Deaths and Marriages offices of
			each state and territory around the country.

			Gender-specific names are back in fashion. Only one name in the top 100 
			appears on 	both the girls’ and boys’ list – Charlie (18th on the boys’ 
			list and 74th on the girls’ list).

			A number of girls’ names from the list can also be
			boys’ names, such as Harper, Jade and Mackenzie. Parents are also
			naming their daughters using popular boys’ names, such as Riley,
			Jayden, Tyler, Leo, Dylan, Hayden, Jordan, Luca, Ashton, Kai, Bailey
			and Alex. Parents are choosing longer, more flowing names for their
			daughters and shorter, more solid-sounding names for their sons.

		</fullText>
		<visibility>restricted</visibility>
		<articleImage>royals.jpg</articleImage>
	</article>
	
	<article>
		<title>What mums really think of childcare</title>
		<author>Stephanie Hansen</author>
		<startDate>02/02/2015</startDate>
		<category>Lifestyle</category>
		<leadText>It's a myth that all stay-at-home mums can afford and want
			to be at home full-time. It’s a myth that Australian working mothers
			want to work full-time. It’s a myth that these mums think it best for
			their kids to attend full-time childcare.</leadText>
		<fullText>This is what Kidspot found when KIDSPOT asked 789 mothers from all 
			over Australia about their current work-life balance and what 
			they needed from childcare and employment to make things work better.

			Most Aussie mums want to work part-time

			Our results show work and childcare is a complicated, emotional and
			fraught experience for most Australian women. One size does not fit
			all. One solution will not work for everyone. This week’s budget
			proposals promote and reward full-time working mothers earning above
			the average wage, but shutting down paid parental leave payments
			(PPL) and getting rid of childcare subsidies for stay-at-home mums
			does not reflect the actual needs of Australian mums.

			Current options – for both employment and childcare – simply do not address
			the need for this flexibility. In fact, current proposals aggravate
			the emotional and complex situation in which thousands of Australian
			families are currently operating. How does it help women already
			struggling with too much on their plates to be accused of ‘double
			dipping’? As one mother told us: “We’re paying nearly $1000 per week
			for the ‘luxury’ of me being able to work full time. It’s
			ridiculous.”

			Childcare makes work harder for women

			All women surveyed said they had mixed feelings about their working
			situation and felt a combination of exhaustion, guilt and pride. The
			happiest mums were the 36 percent who are currently working
			part-time. While they admitted their part-time work was not the most
			satisfying, the flexible arrangement allowed them to be home when
			their children needed them and this contributed to their overall
			satisfaction. The most frustrated were the mums staying at home
			full-time and this frustration was not just expressed in terms of
			finances.

			Single mothers and mothers of twins and triplets struggle financially

			Childcare undoubtedly contributes to these issues. As one mum told
			us, “My biggest concern regarding childcare is marrying work needs
			with care availability. The two rarely match up and my employer is
			often disgruntled and sees me as a challenging employee”.

			A single mum of four had this to say about the struggle and futility
			of full-time work: “I was working full-time even with a six-week-old
			boy. I found that as a family we were having more negatives than
			positives. I also thought, ‘What is the point of nearly my whole pay
			going on childcare?’.”

			A mother of twins said, “I put my twins’ names down before they were
			born at long daycare and am still waiting for spaces … two years
			later.”

			Shift workers and mums in regional areas hit hard

			For mums living outside our major cities the struggle can be even
			harder. One woman living in a rural community told us, “The area
			where I live only provides care for children [over] 15 months old.
			This prevents me from returning to work and prevents my child from
			being able to have care. The centre here needs funding to either
			expand or rebuild to accommodate these needs in our community.”

			Shift-working mothers can also find the childcare challenges
			particularly difficult. Take this mum who used to work in the airline
			industry: “I needed a nanny when my eldest was born to return to my
			shift work job in the airline industry as we have no extended family
			to help and my husband also works shifts. The only flexibility my
			company offered was to return on a part-time basis (reduced hours
			from 37 to 25) but still five days a week starting at 5am. The cost
			of a nanny was more than I made so couldn’t be justified. As a result
			I resigned and feel I’ve lost my career chance now. It’s hard to
			return to my career as I’ve always worked in hospitality or tourism
			in shift-work positions and any job I see advertised requires
			flexible availability seven days a week!”

			Many mums dream of self-employment

			The issue of affordability is also particularly taxing for families with
			twins or triplets, as this mother’s experience shows: “I have twins
			in daycare two days per week. I am unable to afford to have them both
			in day care for each day that I work. I work 38 hours+ per week
			between two jobs. This is a crazy situation as I am constantly
			exhausted and consequently my work quality suffers. That’s not
			acceptable as a RN.”

			While other women are forced to change careers entirely after having
			children, as this mother told us: “I have since retrained in
			childcare, but do not enjoy it as much and the pay is terrible. But
			it is flexible, I work casually when my husband has a day off
			mid-week.”

			Quality of childcare is mum’s biggest concern

			The vast majority of women (78 percent) we spoke to were extremely
			disappointed in their current childcare arrangements. Nearly one in
			four women surveyed had experienced frustrating delays with long
			waiting lists, and a similar number - 24 percent – were concerned
			about the quality of childcare in areas of high demand. As one mum
			told Kidspot when describing the challenges of childcare, “Not
			spending quality time with my kids and ALWAYS being sick. We missed
			so many family events due to illnesses. Two of them ended up in
			hospital numerous times also. [Centres] need more monitoring of
			illnesses and maybe a way for parents to see what their children are
			doing all day. Never had much of an idea of what they were involved
			in every day or how they were treated.”
		</fullText>
		<visibility>public</visibility>
		<articleImage>child.jpg</articleImage>
	</article>

</articles>